so after engineering radio episode 58 product line engineering pop tool.
[Music]
hello everybody to another episode of software engineering radio.
in this episode we're going to talk about product lines again.
so this is the sequel to the original product lines episode.
this time we're going to talk about more in implementation side stuff handing variabilities.
you'll probably also note that this episode is probably the best sound quality ever.
this is because Michael has invested in some really cool recording equipment.
and we have some really professional mics here.
and so you should you should notice the difference hopefully, hopefully that's the plan.
okay, so before we start with today's kind of real core topic.
do we want to briefly very briefly revisit what we talked about in the first product lines episode? do you want to talk about some of these things briefly?
yeah, in the first episode we motivated software product lines while it is a good idea.
well and to recap that it's a good idea whenever you build several products, several similar products.
based on the same assets based on the same components.
and we also talked about problem and solution space.
we talked about features, and we talked about variability in the solution space.
and the problem space where the variability actually stems from.
so today we're going to look a bit more closely at how you can represent and formally model variabilities.
and then in the second part how you can actually implement variable parts of a system in the implementation code.
yeah and in the process of software product line engineering.
we are basically at the step of the domain analyzes where the key goal is first to to scope your product line.
what kind of features, what kind of products do you want to be you want to have in your product line, which ones are out?
you want to define a common vocabulary, some would also call it on ecology taxonomy.
and the outcome would be a domain model.
then further down the road where you have all the dependencies associations between the names the terms that you. just defined.
how they relate to each other.
and at the end you would do a variability analyzes of your products.
you would analyze the features of your products and try to figure out where are the common parts and where do they differentiate.
where is the variability between them.
so what you're saying is that. there is a set of features.
and maybe later than implementation components that is common to all of the products and product line.
and others are optional or whatever the constraint may be.
correct, to start off our discussion on variability I want to come back to our separation between problem and solution space.
and to model variability in the problem space you have several options.
one is a feature model that lists your features basically the requirements get grouped into features.
and you then structure those features hierarchically.
and you note which ones are optional which ones are alternatives and then which ones are mandatory.
you describe your variability and using that means using a feature model.
or in complex situation you would then use a domain-specific language right.
and and the difference is basically that with a feature model what you do is is you configure options from a set of predefined alternatives.
whereas the feature model defines the configuration space the available combinations of features.
okay and so that that only lets you express a certain kind of variability.
which could be called configuration variability or I was called non-structural variability.
and the other kind of variability is if you really want to describe a structure or a business process or something.
as part of your requirements in the problem space and you can't do this with a feature model.
a feature model could describe variants of a given business process for example.
but you can't creatively construct an arbitrary business process.
and the way to do that is to.
use whatever kinds of modeling languages domain-specific languages.
you can do with your activity diagrams in the case of business processes.
and theoretically speaking a feature model is just a specific kind of modeling language.
which allows you to express configuration options.
okay so it's not completely different it's just a different you know expressive power that you. have in your languages.
so we talked about what future models are in the last episode so you should maybe go back and listen to that if you want to know what this is.
but these future models are basically a formulism to describe configuration variability.
and we described what kind of variability you can have and how you would describe it into in the problem space.
now talking about the solution space you have all kinds of variability mechanisms.
and that is actually what we dedicated this episode for right.
but before we before we go there there are something else I briefly want to briefly want to talk about.
and that is before we look about the specific means of implementing implementing variabilities.
talked about about the different kinds of variability in the sense what kind of what things can be variable.
for example in a software system you can either have variable structure or variable behavior.
okay so that's two completely different kinds that need to be addressed somehow.
the other thing is that you.
have might have variability with regards to two functional requirements.
for example do I have to have a billing option in my system or not?
the other thing is variability with regards to non-functional requirements.
such as security, failover, load balancing, scalability.
so it's just different kinds of variability.
there is another kind that's interesting or another dimension that is interesting to distinguish.
and that is features that can be clearly localized modularized.
and others that are more aspectual for example that you would only realize when you.
actually implemented.
when you try to implement this variability.
absolutely, but the nice thing about future models is that.
in your feature model let's in a problem space this distinction is not apparent.
okay so you can abstract over these differences.
and and that is one of the really big advantages of feature models.
compared to for example using some kind of UML elation notation to to describe these kinds of variable aspects of a system.
and just to finish that modular modularized both features are those that can be you know localized.
in the sense that either the system has the building component or it doesn't have it.
whereas aspectual features are a bit more tricky in the implementation.
because for example the feature security is something that might require changes in 15 different places in your resulting system.
and again as we said the feature model doesn't show that and that's actually a big advantage.
because at the time when you define what the features are about the variability is you don't care about these different implementation alternatives.
okay now looking at the solution space.
we are going to discuss the various options the various variability mechanisms that you.
have in the solution space.
and the solution space in this context is specifically source code.
okay so we do not, and that's maybe an outlook to some future episode.
we do not consider how for example you describe their abilities in models or something or documentation.
documentation just generally all the other core assets the other corsets are also important.
but for this episode we focus on the source code variable.
right so we don't consider model during development and the models that are produced as part of that.
as something that we want to vary using variability analyst analysis and variability modeling and stuff.
that's something for maybe a future episode.
so so we are going to focus on source code primarily.
one of the key properties of variability mechanism is its binding time.
binding time means when do you have to make the decision to select one variation at a certain variation point.
and with variation point we mean the location in the source code or your configuration.
where you decide on one of the options one of the alternatives.
or where you set a specific value to identify this variant.
and of course each of these different alternatives which we'll discuss shortly has consequences.
with regards to performance, flexibility, file size, and so on, and also debugging.
and debugging yeah right, the more you do dynamically the harder it is.
that's what you're gonna say?
yes right, so which typical binding times and binding techniques are there?
well the the trivial one or the one that we are very used to is - let's call it source time binding time.
when you do basically cut and paste and manual programming.
and when you just yeah put in different variations in your source code manually.
so that's maybe it's not even really a variability mechanism right.
I mean because that's just bare-bones coding something different?
yeah so source time binding means we really touch manually the code.
or let a generator generate the code at source time.
so yeah you'll probably agree that that manual changes in the source code aren't really what we like to call a variability mechanism.
because it's just what we want to avoid, we don't want to hard-code each of the different variants separately.
so that's not really an alternative right.
right but it becomes an alternative if you use generators.
because then the code is generated from some high level artifacts.
and then you express the variability in the models yes.
okay but we're not again we don't we don't go down this this Rob.
that just want to kind of you know specify whether it would be the point to connect to in some other episode.
the next binding time would be a compile time.
where you would have function overloading, where you would have a pre compiler or template evaluations in in C++.
and now also in Java or for example static aspect weaving this also happens compile-time.
yeah we filled that in Java it's actually compiled time with us.
I mean I thought this is a really compiled time I mean it's not the same as templates right in C++.
from the implementation perspective I'm actually not really sure if this qualifies.
us it's probably compile time, you're probably right.
anyway we can cut this out, that's one of the tricks of podcasters.
that they talk nonsense and that then they'll say are we can cut this out.
and then they leave it in when people have something to laugh about.
okay next one is of course link time.
what do we do after compilation we link it?
in Java this step is not so obvious that's here.
you might associate it with with class loading.
in C++ or other languages it would be the loading the association of gear dll's right.
so the next step is contemplating time or configuration time.
this is especially relevant in the context of whether you was you know a middleware platform as your deployment target.
where you have five million different configuration options that you. can decide upon.
not during programming but rather when you deploy the component of the object.
or whatever the building block is that.
your middle go supports.
whenever you deploy this on to your container or application server then you make some decisions.
for example how big the pool size would be for an enterprise bean or something right.
and finally we have a runtime binding.
and that means really during runtime we make decisions.
in the simplest case this is just a if statement if I'm in that very and then choose this option.
or or a factory or strategy that we select at runtime.
but there are another a real you know boatload of additional mechanisms at runtime.
for example virtual function calls are polymorphism is is a way of late resolving of variants.
things like using factories for instance for instance rating certain classes or components or objects.
it's delegation in general strategy pattern.
and then of course a little bit more advanced meta programming where you use reflection and dynamic runtime code generation.
look at Ruby for example Lisp where you can build complete different program structures at runtime using the meta programming facilities.
let's briefly look at some of the consequences.
so doing things that runtime is probably great because you can decide very late.
so what's what's the drawback at one time?
you have of course the greatest flexibility.
but as always flexibility bytes performance or how you call it.
as soon as.
you have something really flexible the performance is negatively impacted. second thing is code size.
I mean think about for example interceptors that you.
want to use during runtime.
and have a for example also plug in infrastructure plugins company combined with interceptors.
you might optimize it but still if you would have a code generated that does optimally exactly that what it's supposed to do.
exactly this very and only you have the smallest code size and you have the fastest performance.
and and this contrasts runtime binding time with the source time binding and everything in between.
well is it's just like a slow degradation of flexibility and then small increase.
if you start from source and cotton right?
and and the performance is decreased not in every case but generally speaking yeah.
and there is another aspect I guess.
for example I think code that has all its it's different variants in thousands of if statements and strategy patterns.
I mean are you even using you know crazy meta programming stuff?
what about debugging I mean there's also an aspect I guess them here be considered.
I guess debugging is then and in those cases really difficult.
and having source code at the end for your product for your single product.
that just contains those code lines that are actually needed and executed by that variant.
then that is the simplest case and the easiest to debug.
so the question which mechanism you use for implementing a particular variability.
probably then depends on a trade-off between the usual aspects compare performance code size flexibility.
and you can't have all you have to decide for one of these.
yeah right so it's a non-functional properties that you.
were products at the end require it's the requirements basically of your products.
but it's also the available mechanisms for your core asset for for your tools for the technology.
if they're certain the technology doesn't offer this kind of binding time or this kind of variability mechanism.
for example in C you know you don't have reflection out-of-the-box so you you cannot use those those options.
and if void pointers they give you almost as great.
they rule we should add this variability use void pointers for everything.
and and other things are just skills and their environment.
and and how you how you generally deal with your product line.
some in the Indus ofter product line community even advise that choosing from small collection of variability mechanisms.
is sometimes better than having a large set and allowing the developers to use a large set of variability mechanisms.
because new people and the team they will be just confused.
and will be giving them a hard time learning all the variability mechanism and just making more false.
yes it's harder to maintain and harder to develop your variants.
because each of these variability mechanisms in the worst case comes with its own tool.
consider a generator or an aspect weaver right.
so if you use all of them you probably got a result in in to health.
and here we put into the show notes a good reference to a paper written by Felix Bachmann of the sei.
okay and that papers about what just it's about variability - by variability mechanisms.
and it's a it's a nice summary of what's available and what's the current state of research on that topic.
okay so we are going to look at some of these variability mechanisms each in detail.
okay and we're not going to cover generators because that's a different topic.
and we're not going to cover manual changing of the source code.
because that's as we said not a real mechanism after all.
so the first one we're going to look at it briefly is function overloading or method overloading.
I guess everybody knows that from from C++ for example.
you can for example define or Auto Java you can define for example a function or a method that adds two numbers X and Y.
and you can define this function taking two integers as well as taking two doubles right.
and the compiler figures out which of these two overloaded functions to call.
now just to be precise here this is not polymorphism.
okay it's not about resolving the dynamic type of the object at runtime.
and then using this kind of dynamic dispatch table to find out what the method is.
rather the compiler knows what the datatype of the two arguments is double or int.
and then can statically determine what to do. so this is really something that happens at compile time.
although it's SSL typically a little bit confused with with polymorphic overloading.
the next mechanism that we want to discuss is the for example is C and. C++ preprocessor with its macros.
and one of a really good example where it's this kind of variability mechanism has been stressed stressed a lot raised 3.
maybe is the adaptive communication environment short just A's.
which supports a really abundant list of operating system and compiler combinations.
and to achieve this variability in a C++ framework the development team had chosen to use if deaths at many locations.
especially at OS abstraction layer where all the available features of an operating system.
and all the funny and crazy bugs of compilers are selected.
and you would have then a configuration file where you specifically configure your library to obey those features.
and respects of your platform that you're working on.
so what is an F an if death is a preprocessor a statement that gets evaluated before the actual compilations.
that and with that you.
can select conditionally whether a piece of source code is considered in during compilation or not.
so you say if def listened to that feature then you have a piece of code.
and if the variable this and that feature isn't defined during compilation this piece of code is just removed from the compilation process right.
so that's kind of bare-bones brute-force source code modification based on a set of features.
or a set of constants or whatever yes.
and of course just to evaluate each of these mechanisms a little bit.
the problem with this mechanism is that.
it provides absolutely no locality.
so if a certain feature requires changes in 25 different places in the source code.
then you have this if they've such-and-such feature in 25 different locations.
and then CREB becomes your best friend regress.
yes yes, and also if you have certain features that are necessary only if some combination you know.
so this becomes really really complex.
because all the different variants are intermixed in one you know basically in one text file in one piece of source code.
so I think you'll agree that this really scale very well.
but it was the means and and the the the thing to use at a certain point in time.
when when there were no generators available and you know aspect our intention for see.
that's the only option to do it and to be really fast.
because you don't have any runtime impact because you cut out those code segments that are not relevant for your platform.
yeah but at least and see the funny thing is that.
of course the compiler doesn't know how a piece of source code has been created.
so it might happen that you're that you're that you're if that's after throwing out the code that shouldn't be compiled.
results in code that can't be compiled because there is something wrong.
so you don't have any safety net here right.
so it's just this is it's up to you to don't code to not confuse things there.
yeah and just to to relate this there are other much more sophisticated macro systems.
for example and Lisp or in more niche languages like converge or as far as I know also in a language called template Haskell.
which we don't know much about maybe I know thus.
so the point is such a macro or preprocessor system is actually quite powerful.
if it is better integrated with a type system of the host language.
and that's not the case in C it's just text processing so that's the problem.
another mechanism also heavily used in C++ our templates.
we don't talk about template metaprogramming but generally using templates.
separate episode on on crazy template metaprogramming i guess.
using templates for example to specify whether a certain class should be protected by a synchronization log or not.
whether it should using special memory allocator or not.
or generally configuring your classes with other classes and and data types.
so and and the important thing to know here is that.
in C++ templates are actually evaluated during compile time.
in the sense that if you have a templated class that you.
can't parameter with some other template.
for example a very simple case you if you have a collection class and you can template eyes it with the element type of the collection.
then what the C++ compiler does is is it actually creates machine code for each of the different variants.
so there is nothing going on at runtime.
whether you know there is any time some time they may look up off of the parameter.
it really generates two different pieces of machine code and therefore it's very very fast.
because the variability is resolved completely at runtime sorry at compile time.
disadvantages of course if you have 25 different element types for your collection your code size increases by a factor of 25.
because machine code is generated for each of the alternatives.
so let's again this trade-off it's fast about its bigger.
the next mechanism we want to discuss is aspect weaving.
is actually static aspect weaving there's also dynamic aspect weaving.
but we leave that out for for the moment especially since we're talking about compile time mechanism this at this time right.
and so AOP is generally a mechanism to localize cross-cutting concerns.
that are typically spread in all over your source code that is not localized.
and AOP helps you to localize those cross-cutting functionalities into a single or hopefully very few compilation units.
they are then called aspects right.
and what you can do is of course if you have a certain variability that you.
want to inject into the existing code.
you can just weave this in as an aspect.
and aspect weaving if we talk about static aspect weaving weaving happens at compile time.
or more specifically at weave time which is basically the same as compilation.
so the bytecode is actually modified, so there is no runtime overhead almost no runs I'm overhead.
it depends on what kind of aspects you use but generally there is very little and usually none.
and before we get all the comments we talked about aspectj does it today?
yes so indeed and it has yeah and also we're going to have a separate episode and all these AOP details later.
we already identified two potential candidates today who will who will do this. what is interesting is that.
also what can aspects introduce?
so if you look at aspectj and also an aspect c++ the two most popular static aspect weaving tools and use today.
then they can not only add advice code which is you know behavior.
that is executed before after or instead of other behavior.
so you have a method blah blah blah you can have an aspect that says after blah blah blah do something else.
and but what aspects can also do and that is maybe even more interesting here in the context of variant management.
as they can introduce additional operations or additional attributes or additional interface implementations for to existing classes.
and that means that you can localize the structures members classes attributes and so on that you.
need for a given feature into a separate aspect.
and then weave in this aspect.
so you have localized not only the additional behavior you want to have for a specific variant for behavior variability.
but also you can have structural variability localized into an aspect.
and then weave in this additional yeah class structure into the existing classes. and that is quite powerful.
one of the experiences I made applying that is that.
I had to prepare my my plain java source code.
for example with certain hooks that I could later use with with aspects to hook in my my additional functionality my additional features right.
I mean this is you know one of the advantages of aspect-oriented programming.
although this should probably go into this other episode.
is that.
people say you can add all kinds of stuff after the fact.
you don't have to think about things in the in the beginning you can edit.
and I think this is technically true.
but if you want to design or build a really well-designed aspect-oriented program.
then you have to pre think certain variabilities and hooks as in ollo.
so I mean some people use aspect orientation to patch crappy code without modifying it.
as valid use of ILP or let's say it's a valid use aspectj.
but it's not what people PLP people anticipated or expected AOP to be like.
just to have it mentioned there has been some effort by IBM with a high perch a project.
where they actually ambitions to truly encapsulate features and slices of functionality.
and later to basically build a full-fledged application.
you would just merge those hyper slices they call it the the features together to to an application.
but lately there there hasn't been much news about this project right.
we talked about that before but I didn't mention that because I didn't think of it.
there is a new project which they call CM either concern manipulation environment.
and I think that is the successor to high PO che.
but still it's not something that many people talk about these days so it's not really important I guess.
ok so now we leave compile time and we go to deployment time which is the next kind of level of flexibility.
and so for example if you consider we haven't a to application server.
and you confute deploy a certain EJB.
and you can pass in configuration parameters to this EJB.
you can define its pool size, you can say whether it should have all kinds of different security mechanisms applied to it.
you can say whether it should be replicated over different instances of your application server.
and so on and so on and so on.
so this is variability that you.
define during configuration or deployment time.
a specific way of doing that is using interceptors.
and maybe Michael since this is a topic that's probably very near and dear to your heart from your history you want to talk about it?
yeah interceptors are one means to inject new or additional functionality later than the net source time.
you prepare an infrastructure you you build an infrastructure in your application.
that allows you later to inject various interceptors to fulfill certain tasks.
often those tasks are then non-functional concerns like for example security or transactions or so.
in distributed infrastructures one way to implement such an interceptor infrastructure is to.
use the factory and proxies.
so the factory is asked for the proxy.
and the proxy then has a set of interception hooks in it. that as soon as.
the client accesses the proxy the it will transparently apply all interceptors in its chain.
and basically the the proxy allows you to shield the actual implementation component.
from the complexity of managing all those interceptors and applying the strategies that they might contain.
so in typical hooks where you can put in behavior is again before and after.
so if a client calls a method on the object in fact of course it calls it on the proxy that's the whole point of a proxy.
then the proxy may be calls on the interceptors that are configured a method called before invocation.
and passes in the method that's called the method name that's called in the parameters.
and then the Interceptor can do something for example logging the method call or checking some permissions or doing whatever else.
and then the proxy forwards the call to the original component.
so before and after trusted and aspect orientation are typical hooks for interceptors.
the next variability mechanisms that we want to discuss our load time mechanisms.
in in static languages such as C and.
C++ you can load different libraries dynamically linked libraries dll's.
in in the windows world that define the same entry points.
and entry points are basically your API that is used to access the functionality contained within the library.
those entry points need to state it's the same.
but besides that you.
can then choose various implementations various compatible libraries.
that you exchange based on the kind of variation you.
want to achieve here.
and in in Java the Panda here the equivalent is the this class loading.
although the variability mechanism in fact will be a runtime solution using polymorphism right.
so so and in in DL else what happens is that.
basically basically when a DLL is loaded a bunch of pointers are you know redirected.
to point to the actual entry points in in the file that has been mapped into memory.
now so that's why it's a link time or a load time mechanism.
and with Java class loading you would have to have Java interfaces specified.
and then have placed their implementations in different class for a DG pattern or bridge pattern right.
okay so that's actually the right the next mechanism let's look at runtime mechanism polymorphism.
I don't know how much we really have to talk about that.
because polymorphism I think is something everybody knows.
the idea is that if you have different subclasses that.
each define the same method.
and you call this method then the actual code that's executed depends on the dynamic subtype.
so you have this table that dispatch is the the operation you call to the specific method.
that's actually the distinction people make the operation of the method that that that depends of that that corresponds to the dynamic type.
what potential further mechanisms to do languages such as Java offer us to implement variability?
well in Java there isn't very much actually.
what you can do is for example you can dynamically call methods by using Java reflection.
so based on some configuration option that maybe it's just the name of a method you want to call.
you can dynamically find this method and then call it by reflection.
so it's not just polymorphism or something it's really determining the name of a method that should be called by whatever means.
for example you can write the name of the method into a configuration file read this file.
and then dynamically call the method without knowing that this method exists on the class.
or without having it defined in some kind of interface.
so you can call any method by using reflection.
and of course if the method isn't there we get some kind of exception.
so that's that's rather boring you can't do very much in Java.
however in somewhat more sophisticated our languages you have much more extensive ways of meta programming.
for example you can change the meaning of certain trivial or built-in operations.
for example if you call a method in C loss which is the common list object system.
then you can change the interpreter in a way so that calling a method means something different.
for example first to some log output and then invoke the actual method.
it's kind of a kind of aspect orientation.
and if people know this kind of meta object protocol stuff that has been implemented in C loss.
is actually the precursor to two aspect orientation in other languages such as small talk or self or Ruby.
you have similar ways of doing this kind of meta programming.
there are very for example in Ruby and we talked about that in the episode and ruby dsls.
so when a ruby class is loaded or if what when the compiler reads the definition the code that defines a ruby class.
then the interpreter actually interprets this definition.
and as part of this this interpretation is part of the class definition.
you can execute other methods which in turn changed this definition.
so you can basically have self-modifying code.
so you can have a class definition that as part of its own definition called a method called add the following attributes. : name first name last name.
and what this method does is it dynamically adds the attributes name first name and last name to the class that's currently defined.
now this sounds like something that you can you know used to shoot you.
into into your own foot.
that is what I wanted to say as something as somebody who's rather conservative.
under said I I would have asked how could I miss you that.
and how could I actually later than know what's going on how could I D bug such a system.
you know I'm just I like to have to reply that but.
so so you're kind of saying this dynamic languages with all this meta programming stuff.
it's not really it's too complex and no you're not misuse it.
and I just want to say you can do the same maybe even worse things in static languages.
look at this C++ template metaprogramming stuff isn't that a misuse in a static language.
but I have a harder time doing it not right.
okay yeah I mean this is a very powerful mechanism you can do all kinds of crazy things.
on the other side it is extremely powerful.
and all the features that people talk about about Ruby but the hyper on Ruby is this meta programming stuff.
Ruby on Rails is implemented based on this stuff completely.
but it's shielded by a simple programming interface by a simple DSL basically.
I'm not saying that you.
have to expose all these things.
that's probably true for all those mechanisms you want to provide a nice way of configuring them of using them.
you can do this using modal's, you can do this view do this using internal dia cells and Ruby.
you can do it using macros in in silos.
so that's clear, you can also hide it after a behind normal classes in C++.
the boost library for example uses template metaprogramming to the extreme internally.
but you as the user of the you don't see this.
so that's that's alright, the same is true for Ruby.
you don't want to expose this to the framework user.
but that's probably true for most variabilities you want to still use the mechanism.
okay here I free okay, okay I think we just discussed a nice set of variability mechanisms.
something that that I want to mention here also is that.
in some cases it might be useful to use combinations of those variability mechanisms.
for example use some configuration files maybe even format them using some xml style.
here xml makes really sense for for configuration files.
and then read out this configuration while you declaratively state your configuration.
and use some runtime or load time mechanism to then configure and customize your product.
I would I would like to extend the start even a little bit further.
so what you say is that.
what you should do is you should capture the variabilities in some kind of configuration file.
I use different MSI you build a model of this configuration?
not really I mean that's what happens.
and then you can once you have this model that clearly captures these configuration options.
you can decide whether you build an interpreter of that model which reads these options at runtime and change the stuff at runtime.
or whether you build a generator which reads these things during code generation or sauce time more or less.
and then generates different code.
so the essence of variability management maybe is to formally capture the variabilities.
the valid options and the concrete selections you make for a specific product in your product line.
and then you have all the different ways of implementing that but the preconditions capturing that nicely.
yeah here I really like to state something I read in the paper by Felix Parkman.
it's basically the goal of variability in software product lines is to maximize return of investment.
and here it goes on yada yada but the key is basically that you.
have to cost factors.
one is to build in the variability and one is to exercise the variability.
why why is it why is it a cost factor to use the variability?
isn't that the benefit of reusing things that you've put in for?
yes but it's it can be a benefit in the in the case of the of generators for example.
you have a large really large cost to build in the variability to build a generator to build the metamodel etc.
to learn about the generator and it's very easy.
it's so cheap to exercise the variability with other mechanisms.
that the built in to build in variability is is quite easy for example with the strategy.
but to implement than the various strategies the concrete ones basically to exercise the variability you have a higher cost.
and when you here have very many options there are many strategies then there's cost of exercising this variability explodes.
and and so what you should be looking for whatever the message is think about both costs.
think about how much it costs to building this variability end to exercise it.
and the combination of both try to optimize that for the use case for the kind of variability you have that this variation point.
so this again where economies of scale come in.
if you use the variability in different ways really really really often.
then the cost you have to invest initially to build it for example this generator doesn't really count.
because you save a lot of cost when you reuse it and exercise it over and over again.
if this ratio is not that you know big if you only use it you know fewer times then you. might not want to take the initial invest.
so what is this fewer for example in the case of the generators that you.
are familiar with?
you mean the ratio and the ratio and it starts to make sense.
I mean this is a really tough question because it depends on how much effort it is to build the generator.
and that really depends on a specific kind of variability you have.
I mean you you said before building a generator is very very very very much effort?
that's I wouldn't I mean I certainly wouldn't subscribe to that.
it's more effort than just using strategy pattern.
it's not such a big effort for markers but for everybody just for people who are used to using the tools it's not a big effort.
so you have to you have to add into this equation the effort that it takes to get to learn the tools with which you can't do it.
same is true you know if you ask Edwin Collier or or Gregor kisailus that will say no problem with a spec J.
just through this weird point cut and and some some advice here and there and some introduction and that's done.
but if you don't know aspectj getting to the point where this is easy it's quite a lot of work. same for generators right.
so so this is another dimension how much how many additional tools do you have to learn.
in case of for example the strategy peridot to learn new tools.
you just have to read the Gogh book and understand it. in case of C+ the templates same thing.
you don't have to use another tool you just have to understand weird C++ template metaprogramming.
so the effort of getting to the point where using the variability manic mechanism is feasible is another pre investment.
okay I agree with that so where does this leave us?
tough discussion now you can of course associate with all the variability mechanisms the binding time.
we we hinted already somewhat added at which.
wearability mechanism is udit for what kind of binding time requires a certain binding time.
and there is some variation in it but the outline we gave should be sufficient right.
so I think this more or less concludes this episode.
we do we have something else but we disagree upon so we can you can know.
we leave that for the next step exactly.
when when starting this episode we actually started in a somewhat different fashion.
and we noticed that we didn't agree on what we wanted to say.
so we said ok forget about that postpone this to some later episode.
we will talk about these more esoteric things.
and hopefully we can agree about on what we want to talk about beforehand.
ok so stay tuned for more discussions and software product lines and thanks for listening bye.
[Music]
thanks for listening to software engineering radio.
if you want to get more information about software engineering radio or if you want to give us feedback.
please go to our website at se - radio dot net.
you can also contact the team at team at SAE - radio dotnet.
although we prefer entries in our comment system on the website so other people can see what you think.
software engineering radio wants to thank Henning poly for the intro and outro music.
as well as Lipson for providing the bandwidth.
this episode of se radio as well as all other episodes is licensed under Creative Commons license.
see the software engineering radio website for details you.
[Music]